There's a study that recently released
that has two sides of the health aisle
disagreeing. And I ran across a comment
by a prominent cardiologist that I
honestly thought was a bit dismissive of
the findings of this study that
indicates that highfat cheese may
provide some protection from dementia
and could a similar story be true for
heavy cream as well. So, I'd like to
show you the data as always, but I'd
also like to point out several glaring
weaknesses in the counterarguments
springing forward against the study
findings and why we may want to hold off
our initial urge to dismiss this study.
For example, did you know that this
isn't the only study indicating a
beneficial relationship between cheese
and dementia? Well, we'll get into that,
but let's begin with the initial study
which has made quite the stir.
Essentially, the study investigates the
relationship between dairy and dementia
in around 27,000 people over 25 years.
The conflict was over the results coming
out of the comparison between highfat
and low-fat cheeses. So, highfat being
defined as anything above 20% fat. So,
cheeses like Brie, Camell, Gouda, uh,
cheddar, and plenty of others. So,
what's the big deal with cheese? Let's
start there before we touch on cream as
well. Here's what's causing the
friction. I'm showing you all the data
in the table, but if you're a visual
learner, just focus on the graph that I
made based on that data. Essentially, we
have highfat cheeses and low-fat cheeses
at varying quantities of intake on the
left side. The middle 1.0 line indicates
no difference in dementia risk compared
to consuming the lowest amounts of
cheese. If the lines and dots move to
the left, that means that there's
reduced risk of dementia. And if they
move to the right, well, that's
obviously increased risk. You probably
see it now. The greatest consumption of
highfat cheese, but not low-fat cheese,
is linked to reduced risk of dementia.
That's the result. But then a bunch of
people started commenting on the study
providing critique. Some of it good and
some of it bad. For example, this is an
associative study, but if you've been
here for a hot minute, you'll know that
uh that's not a good reason to dismiss a
study. And as usual, the researchers
performed a series of adjustments to
control for factors that could
potentially explain this relationship.
And yet, the results that you just saw
remained even after all these
adjustments. So to me, if we're going to
accept well-performed associative
studies in favor of, I don't know,
walnuts or fiber and so on, then we
should be equal in our treatment here as
well. I don't see anything here that
jumps out at me as a glaring issue. Now,
that said, one excellent critique, which
is always a potential problem in these
kinds of studies, is something called
reverse causation. Meaning that people
could be switching to a low-fat dairy
because they've been instructed to by
their physician or nutritionist to
switch due to poor health, even poor
brain health, which would explain why
there's no such beneficial relationship
with low-fat dairy. And in fact, it may
exclude anyone out of the highfat cheese
condition, which is developing early
signs of dementia, therefore
artificially indicating a positive
relationship. Now, on the face, that's a
good argument. But we should give the
authors credit because it's not like
they just found the relationship and
then thought to themselves, "Okay, job's
done. Nothing else here for us to think
about." They foretold these dark
critical times and performed further
work called sensitivity analyses, like a
lag analysis. And after performing these
analyses to tease out the real
relationship, they were still able to
identify a reduced risk of dementia from
eating highfat cheese. So the
relationship stands after addressing
many of the concerns. Now of course
there are still limitations as there are
with all studies and in this case a
major one is the same one for many
epidemiological studies have. They
measure nutrition once only at the
beginning of the study which was 25
years ago. You can imagine that over 25
years people's diets may have changed
called diet drift. The researchers did
try to address this by looking at the
results in 2014 and assessing nutrition
and then again at 2020. The final point
of the study and the relationship
between the highfat and reduced dementia
risk was lost. That means that they
restricted the analysis to people who
had not changed their diet significantly
and the relationship vanished. But I
will also mention that the relationship
may have weakened, but they also lost
35% of their participants, which reduces
the amount of data that you'd have
available to detect a relationship if
there were one. Either way, we should be
aware of the limitations as they exist.
Still, I didn't want to leave it there
because I've run across multiple people
discussing this study, but no one has
increased the scope to look at broader
literature, which is where I started to
lean in on some of these other studies,
including a randomized control trial,
which makes everyone drool. Okay, maybe
just the science nerds. Anyway, one
critique that I found ironic brought up
was that Japanese people tend to have
low rates of dementia, yet their cheese
consumption is very low. This is weak
evidence because it's known as
ecological evidence. And I almost
laughed out loud when I ran across this
study which was done in people from
Japan. Essentially, it shows why
ecological data can be so weak because
the study followed people over a few
years and compared those who eat cheese
compared to those who don't. The
finding, well, look for yourself. We
have a risk of dementia on the vertical
axis. So, so to clearly read this, if
the lines go down, that means that there
is more dementia cases, and clearly
there's a separation between the red and
the blue, the non-consumers of cheese
and the consumers, respectively. These
data tell us that Japanese older adults
that consume cheese have lower rates of
dementia, counterintuitively, if we were
to believe the weaker forms of data.
Still, this is a relatively short
duration study and the researchers made
far fewer adjustments than our main
study that we've been going over. So,
it's entirely possible that there's some
residual confounding going on here. That
means that something else may explain
this divergent relationship. I'd also
like to point out that the difference is
quite small. Of course, this could
simply be because the study only lasted
a couple years as opposed to 25 years.
That all said, this wasn't the only
study to indicate a healthful
relationship between cheese and
dementia, though there are also studies
that showed no relationship. That could
come down to any number of different
reasons from the population study to the
fact that some studies may have had more
people consuming low-fat cheeses, and
the list goes on. The main point that I
want you to get from this is that
there's either no relationship between
cheese and dementia or there's a good
relationship, more cheese, less risk of
dementia. Now, I'll be coming back to
this, but before we do, let's get into
this randomized control trial, an
attempt to indicate a causitive
relationship between cheese and brain
health. And in fact, before we even get
to that, I'm going to be discussing the
relationship butter, milk, and meat have
with dementia, as well as people with
high genetic risk of Alzheimer's
disease, different types of dementia,
and the interaction with these foods and
more. Now, I'm covering all that in the
extended analysis, which is included as
a physionic insider, as you may already
know. Now, I've said this before, but
I'll say it again. You also get all
these perks right over here. Plus, I
created my own physionic AI based on all
my work that you can ask questions to.
So, yeah, pretty nifty. Anyway, to
become an insider and get access to all
my work in written, audio, and video
format, all ad free, check out the link
in the description. Become an insider
today.
We have a loan study that looks at
cheese consumption and brain function.
And in the study, they had one group of
people that were told to consume
fermented cheese for three months and
then told to stop consuming said cheese
and switch to non-fermented cheese for 3
months. They had brain assessments taken
before and after each period. And the
results was
well not that exciting. Essentially the
fermented cheese which was kombell did
not provide any benefit in regard to
cognitive function. But the
non-fermented cheese made of mozzarella
and cream cheese did provide a very
slight improvement in cognitive
function. So kind of meh results, but at
least we can say that in no situation
did cheese lead to worsening. Though
there were no comparisons against non-
cheese consuming groups, which would
have been a nice addition. Either way,
this study lightly corroborates that
cheese in general may have positive
effects, though some of the specifics
are pretty murky. Okay, allow me to take
a step back and I can literally take a
step back and simplify all this before
we discuss how all this is proposed to
work. Now, I've been doing a lot of
cheese defending. I'm out here with my
sword and knight's armor defending
cheese's honor as it relates to
dementia. However, even in the face of
all the data that we've been going over,
there's a lot of darkness in areas that
the light, i.e. data, doesn't shine, the
current evidence indicates that cheese
is at least not harmful to brain
function. And there's some indications
that it can have a mild protective
relationship against brain disorders
known as dementia as a class. Beyond
that, we only have one or two studies
that look at highfat cheeses
specifically. So, it's extremely
difficult to tease out what the truth
really is without more light, again,
i.e. data to illuminate the way. If
you're not a cheese lover, I don't see
any compelling evidence here that cheese
is going to be the next cure for
dementia. So, feel free to continue
avoiding it if it's considering it's
unlikely to be a major player. However,
if you are a cheese lover, I'd be
heartened by the data presented here.
So, I would keep munching away knowing
that there's decent chance that cheese,
especially highfat cheeses, may be
providing me with some brain benefit and
simply aligns well with my already
cultivated habits. And speaking of that
brain benefit, how exactly is cheese
providing us with that said benefit? So,
unfortunately, these studies aren't
designed to identify mechanisms or at
least for the most part because they're
associative. That said, the one
randomized control trial that we went
over did identify some changes in a
potent brain boosting molecule called
BDNF or brain derived neurotrphic
factor. However, counterintuitively, it
was raised for the fermented cheese, the
cheese that did not show cognitive
benefit. Generally, this BDNF is known
to be involved in synaptogenesis. So, it
allows brain cells called neurons to
create new synapses or communication
points between neurons. It's possible
that 3 months is too short to really
identify a longlasting protection
against dementia, but this is a lot of
speculation that's not more than strong
evidence. Alternatively, the main
analysis that we've been over discusses
the interaction between different
molecules within highfat cheeses
specifically. For example, different
fats. Yes, they contain saturated fats,
but the type of saturated fats can
differ or the combination with other
nutrients like vitamin K2 can also play
a role. In fact, vitamin K2 is found in
abundance in the brain, allowing brain
cells to survive as well as allows them
to create molecules necessary to
maintain the structure of the neuron
called myelin. Now, there's so much more
to get into there, but it's beyond the
scope of this video. The main point is
that we have no real clue why the
relationship between highfat cheese and
lower dementia risk is present. Though
we have a few ideas. All right. I did
mention way at the beginning that the
researchers also looked at cream and the
relationship to dementia. And here again
they showed a healthful relationship as
in reduced risk of dementia with more
heavy cream consumption. And again
applying the same critiques as before
and combating those critiques.
Similarly, remember the sensitivity
analyses that I mentioned, the heavy
cream relationship to reduce dementia
remained true. Unfortunately, there are
very few studies on the topic, so it's
tough to corroborate these data. That
being the case, an already somewhat
shaky confidence gets even shakier when
trying to create actionable takeaways
for heavy cream consumption. I think
that we need more data, even more than
with the highfat cheese. But this one
analysis indicates that if you're
concerned about heavy cream consumption
and your risk of dementia, if that's
your highly specific concern, then don't
be. There's no doubt that I'd be
extremely interested to understand what
is going on here, the mechanisms that
underline this relationship. But until
then, you might be interested to
understand how a particular fat helps us
combat dementia. Nope, it's not really
in cheese or cream. I covered right
here. Thanks for tuning in and enjoy
your cheese. Ratatouille.